# Siqi Wu

Ann Arbor, MI, USA | siqiwu@umich.edu | https://avalanchesiqi.github.io/

#### RESEARCH SUMMARY

I aim to derive principles for responsible social systems, with my core expertise in large-scale quantitative analysis and collaboration with experts in social science, communication, and political science. I work towards my goal through a variety of methods – from curating unique social media datasets, to modeling collective user behavior, to building algorithmic audits for identifying negative platform effects, to designing and testing new HCI systems.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Research Fellow | University of Michigan. Ann Arbor, MI, USA

2020.09 - present

- ^ First 20 months working remotely as a research consultant due to pandemic and visa.
- Center for Social Media Responsibility. Adviser: Paul Resnick

Projects include (1) measuring cross-partisan discussions on YouTube; (2) characterizing concept difference and (3) quantifying the impacts of annotator demographics in labeling hate, offensive, and toxic social media content; (4) calibrating prevalence estimation methods for online problematic speech; (5) designing effective training procedure for crowdsourced labeling; (6) auditing polarized recommendations in YouTube recommender system.

# Research Fellow | Australian National University. Canberra, ACT, Australia

2020.09 - 2021.03

- Computational Media Lab. Adviser: Lexing Xie

Projects include (1) measuring collective human attention across different social platforms; (2) picturing global media consumption during COVID-19.

# Software Engineer | MicroStrategy, Inc. Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China

2015.09 - 2016.05

- Big Data Engine team. Built Apache Spark alike engine to process massive data.

# Software Developer Intern | Baidu, Inc. Beijing, China

2014.12 - 2015.02

- Baidu Maps team. Developed a tool to collect realtime traffic status.

### **EDUCATION**

# Australian National University. Canberra, ACT, Australia

2016.06 - 2020.09

- PhD in Computer Science. Advisers: Lexing Xie and Marian-Andrei Rizoiu
- Thesis: Measuring collective attention in online content: Sampling, engagement, and network effects

# University of Melbourne. Melbourne, VIC, Australia

2013.07 - 2015.07

- Master of Information Technology. Adviser: Richard Sinnott
- Thesis: An architecture for big data processing and visualisation of traffic data

# Tianjin University. Tianjin, China

2008.09 - 2012.06

- Bachelor of Electronics Engineering. Adviser: Yugong Wu

# **AWARDS**

- AAAI ICWSM Best Paper Finalist '21
- ACM CSCW Best Paper Honorable Mention '19
- Google PhD Fellowship '18

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- \* Equal authorship
- 11. ACT: Active crowd training for crowdsourced labeling
  - Wu\*, Rajadesingan\*, Budak, Garrett, Sude, and Resnick. Under review
- 10. Whose advantage? Measuring attention dynamics across YouTube and Twitter on controversial topics Lee\*, **Wu**\*, Ertugrul\*, Lin, and Xie. *ICWSM* '22. Full paper
- 9. Cross-partisan discussions on YouTube: Conservatives talk to liberals but liberals don't talk to conservatives **Wu** and Resnick. *ICWSM* '21. Full paper, **best paper finalist**
- 8. AttentionFlow: Visualising influence in networks of time series Shin\*, Tran\*, **Wu**\*, Mathews, Wang, Lyall, and Xie. *WSDM* '21. Demo paper
- 7. Unsupervised cyberbullying detection via time-informed Gaussian mixture model Cheng, Shu, **Wu**, Silva, Hall, and Liu. *CIKM* '20. Full paper
- 6. Variation across scales: Measurement fidelity under Twitter data sampling **Wu**, Rizoiu, and Xie. *ICWSM* '20. Full paper
- 5. Estimating attention flow in online video networks
  - Wu, Rizoiu, and Xie. CSCW '19. Full paper, best paper honorable mention
- 4. How is attention allocated? Data-driven studies of popularity and engagement in online videos **Wu**. *WSDM '19*. Doctoral consortium
- 3. Beyond views: Measuring and predicting engagement in online videos **Wu**, Rizoiu, and Xie. *ICWSM* '18. Full paper
- 2. Will this video go viral? Explaining and predicting the popularity of YouTube videos Kong, Rizoiu, **Wu**, and Xie. WWW '18. Demo paper
- 1. SMASH: A cloud-based architecture for big data processing and visualization of traffic data **Wu**, Morandini, Sinnott. *DSDIS* '15. Full paper

# **TEACHING**

- Teaching assistant in ANU graduate course COMP6490 Document analysis ('17, '18)
- Teaching assistant in ANU undergraduate course COMP1030 Art of computing ('17)

### **STUDENTS**

- Alex Liu (UMich PhD)
- Cai Yang (ANU undergrad)

### **COMMUNITY SERVICE**

- ICWSM '22 Student Volunteer and Scholarship Chair
- Senior program committee: ICWSM ('22)
- Program committee/Reviewer: ICWSM ('17, '18, '21), CSCW ('19-'22), WebSci ('22), ASONAM ('21), WWW ('19, '20), AAAI ('19), ACM TOIS ('20), EPJ Data Science ('21)

### MISC.

- Organizing: co-organized the Computational Media Lab winter workshop '19
- Certificates: 16 MOOC courses, e.g., machine learning, social network analysis, algorithms, etc.
- Running: 18 100+km events, 50+ (ultra) marathons finisher, 2:57 marathon